PAUL M. VERA MERN DEVELOPER

GITHUB.COM/PAUL88VERA | PAULVERA-PORTFOLIO.HEROKUAPP.COM
SAN ANTONIO, TEXAS 78221

SUMMARY

Web Developer with over 5 years of industry and educational setting experience in front-end development, and a new insight to back-end development after completing a coding bootcamp with the University of Texas at Austin. Passionate about learning new technologies, frameworks, and creating functional applications.

SKILLS

HTML Express.js Apollo Server CSS/SCSS/SASS Restful API Heroku

Bootstrap 5 MongoDB JSON Web Token

Python React.js Git/GitHub

JavascriptVue.jsMVC FrameworkJQuerySQL/NoSQL/MySQL/GraphQLVisual Studio CodeNode.js/NPMPC/MACAdobe Creative Suite

PROFESSIONAL WORK HISTORY

Information Technology Teacher

Southwest Legacy Highschool | San Antonio, TX | Aug 2021 - Current

- Developed Texas Essential Knowledge and Skills aligned curriculum for Computer Science I, Computer Maintenance, Principles of IT Fundamentals, and Web Design courses for secondary students.
- Taught secondary students the latest trends and practices in UX/UI development which include CSS animations, dark mode implementation, contrasting typography, and addition of gradients.
- Bootstrap 5 was introduced after CSS concepts were obtained to quicken production.
- Provided a two-week bootcamp for Responsive Web Design that includes HTML and CSS basic coding structure, element usage and definitions, best practices and personal knowledge in graphic design, and layout design using flex or grid to create responsive pages.
- Created responsive front-end websites from wireframes using web applications such as Figma and Adobe XD.
- JavaScript was used to create event listeners for specific Document Object Models or (DOM) to create a sense of user interaction.
- Implemented and trained students using Python language curriculum provided by Amazon called ProjectSTEM.
- Visual Studio Code editor UI was taught to secondary students for the creation and implementation of their coding projects.
- My responsibilities included building TEKS aligned curriculum, managing the Cybersecurity Program, sponsoring the CyberPatriot Club, and Proctoring End of Year (EOY) CompTIA certification exams, (CompTIA ITF+).

Freelance Web Developer

VERAfied Creations | San Antonio, TX | Feb 2016 - Current

- Communicated with business owners to create websites based on their given criteria and ideal future company growth/expansion.
- Developed mockups and prototypes using Adobe XD and Figma.
- Created custom end-to-end React.js sites that used Node.js, Express.js, MongoDB, and JSX.
- Helped owners implement new domain setup.
- MVC framework was used to create reusable code and to increase productivity.
- Variations of elements were created for A/B Testing to find the best results for user experience.
- · Created logos and implemented content marketing strategies that significantly gained new leads.
- Search Engine Optimization (SEO) processes such as increasing website speed, targeting keywords, and creating backlinks were used to get a better website ranking to increase website popularity.
- Landing Pages were designed to compel users to sign up for newsletters or for more information on the specific topic.
- Opt-In Email Marketing was implemented to gain user information to add to our mailing list for further discounts.
- Developed authorized admin logins using JSON Web Token and MySQL, NoSQL, or GraphQL depending on type of website wanted by owners.

Creative Designer

Codeup | San Antonio, TX | Mar 2021 - Aug 2021

- Created digital and print designs such as vector assets, billboard compositions, social media campaigns, mailing print campaigns, brochures, and merchandise for the company.
- Maintained the WordPress CMS for the entire company and created new web pages upon reguest.
- Developed UX/UI driven web pages for employees and students such as graduation web pages that showcased their completed final group projects, embedded specific social media hyperlinks leading to students for possible employer hire, and created employee information pages for company wide announcements/knowledge.
- JavaScript was used to add conditional logic to certain pages to add video players, user interaction animations, and embedding Google Maps API's using additional plugins for WordPress (Insert Headers and Footers by WPBeginner the plugin installed).
- Created embedded hyperlinks in PDF documents that were distributed to Codeup sponsors and affiliates.
- Resized, converted, and manipulated various medium to fit company distribution needs using Visual Studio Code, Canva, and the Adobe
 Creative Suite.
- Updated UX/UI design and responsiveness on webpages upon request.
- Communicated with Marketing Director to and Marketing Team during daily AGILE meetings to maintain, and meet production dates.

Web Design & Animation Teacher

New Braunfels High School | New Braunfels, TX | Aug 2017 - Aug 2021

- Developed Texas Essential Knowledge and Skills aligned curriculum for Web Design and 2D/3D Animation courses for secondary students.
- Taught secondary students design principles and elements of design in order to create well balanced and user-friendly end products.
- Bootstrap 4 was used for in-class competitions to create visually appealing web pages quickly.
- Adobe Dreamweaver UI was taught for the creation and implementation of coding projects.
- Adobe Animate, Adobe Illustrator, and Autodesk Maya were taught to render 3D animations and create vector assets for webpages to
 produce a unique aesthetic for their websites.
- Provided research tips, understanding of documentation, and usage of Adobe Dreamweaver, Adobe Animate, Adobe Illustrator, Adobe Photoshop, Adobe Premiere Pro, and Adobe XD software.
- Direct students won awards in Business Professional of America competitions: 1st Place National winners for the 3D Animation in 2017, 2nd Place National for 3D Animation in 2018, and 1st Place State Graphic Design winner in 2019.
- My responsibilities included building TEKS aligned curriculum, managing Business Professionals of America organization (BPA) finances for NBISD, and coordinating state competitions for the Business Professionals of America organization (BPA) at NBISD.

PROJECTS

Old Fashioned: <u>damp-temple-66157.herokuapp.com</u> | Full Stack Developer

Old-Fashioned is a guide with a pre-existing library of drink recipes enjoyed around the world. (Currently re-developing in REACT framework - https://github.com/paul88vera/old-fashioned-react)

- UX/UI designer for project
- Developed authorization for Sign Up and Login pages
- Technologies Used: MySQL, Express.js, Sequelize, Handlebars, Bcrypt, Nodemon, and DotENV

Tech Blog: aqueous-depths-39284.herokuapp.com | Full Stack Developer

Techie Blog is a website template for creating blog posts. It also allows commenting and voting once logged in.

- Created a MVC framework for Users, Posts, Votes, and comments.
- Used Bcrypt to create encrypted posts to database.
- Technologies Used: MySQL, Express.js, Sequelize, Handlebars, Bcrypt, and DotENV

Social Network API: github.com/paul88vera/social-network-api | Back-End Developer

Social Network API is a backend only API for use in a social media app. It can be implemented with a completed front-end.

- Created a MVC framework for Users and Thoughts.
- Developed schema and routes for Users and Thoughts
- Technologies Used: Node.js, Express.js, and Mongoose

EDUCATION

Certification of Completion UT Code | University of Texas at Austin Bachelor of Fine Arts in Video Production | The Art Institute of San Antonio

CERTIFICATIONS

CompTIA ITF+ | CompTIA EC-12 242 Technology Applications Certification | Texas Education Agency